Hello Namaskar Jai Hind Vande Mataram.  You are watching
Jio News and we have brought for you
quick big news of selected importance from the country, world and your state and city.  But
before that, if you have not subscribed to our channel, then
subscribe to the channel and turn on the bell notification
and like and share this video as much as possible.
Today's question for you before looking at the big news.  With the help of which organ do fishes
breathe?  Option A: Nose,
Option B: Skin, Option C:
Gills, Option D: Lungs.  Answer this question by
commenting and tell us which state and city
's news do you want to see more?
Tell us by commenting so that we
can show more news of your state or city.  Let us now see
today's quick big news.
Dearness allowance in UP was increased by 2% to 60%.
Benefit to 28 lakh employee pensioners.
Arrears will be given from January 2026.  On May 21, the UP government
increased the dearness allowance (DA) of state employees and pensioners by 2%.
Now 60% dearness allowance will be given instead of 58%.  There are
16 lakh employees and 12
lakh pensioners in the state.  That means a total of 28 lakh
employees will get its benefit.
Deepak Kumar, Additional Chief Secretary of the State Finance Department,
said that from January 1, 2026, employees and
pensioners will be paid at the rate of 60% dearness allowance.  The
increased dearness allowance from January 1 to April 30 will be
deposited in the employees' provident fund account i.e. PF as arrears.  Whereas the
increased dearness allowance from May 1 will be
given in the salary received in June.  The
arrears of increased dearness allowance from January 1 to April 30 will be
deposited in the pension account of pensioners.  The
increased dearness allowance from May 1 will be given along with the pension received in June.
OBC Commission was formed for Panchayat elections in UP.
Retired Justice Ram Avtar Singh
Chairman.  Reservation will be decided on their report.   The
UP government has constituted the state-
level rural body dedicated Backward Classes
Commission (OBC Commission) for the Panchayat elections.  The
tenure of the commission will be 6 months and
retired judge of Allahabad High Court Ram Avtar Singh has been
made the chairman of the commission.  Along with this,
two retired Additional District Judges
Brijesh Kumar Santosh Vishwakarma and two
retired IAS Dr. Arvind Chaurasia and M
SP Singh have been included in the commission.  The commission's
report may come by November 2026.
After this the reservation will be decided.  It has become clear that
Panchayat elections will be held only after the Assembly elections in 2027
and on February 4, 2025, the High Court had
ordered the government to constitute a commission.
Now the allegations of suppressing the case regarding RGGhar will be investigated.  Kolkata High Court
orders formation of SIT.  The report has to be submitted by June 25.  The
Kolkata High Court has
ordered an investigation into allegations of suppression of the Ariggar rape and murder case.  The court has
ordered the formation of a three-member CBI SIT.  It will be headed by the
Joint Director of CBI's Eastern Region
and the SIT will have to submit its report by June 25.  The
court has given this order
on the petition filed by the parents of the victim.  On
March 17 last year, the parents had
accused the CBI of not investigating the case properly and suppressing the matter.  The
Supreme Court had given permission to the parents to
file a petition in the Kolkata High Court.
Singing Vande Mataram is mandatory in all Madrasas of Bengal.
CAA implemented.
Gave land to BSF for fencing.  12 big decisions of the government in 12 days.  The
West Bengal government has made
singing of Vande Mataram mandatory in all madrasas under the state's Minority Affairs and Madrasa Education Department.
This order was issued on May 19.
According to the information, this came to light on Thursday.
According to the government order, this rule will be immediately applicable to government
model madrasas, government aided and
unaided madrasas.
After the new order, it will now be
mandatory to sing Vande Mataram in the morning prayer meeting i.e. assembly before the class starts.
Earlier, during the morning prayers in madrasas, the
national anthem, Jana Gana Mana and poet
Ghulam Mustafa's
Bangla song Anant Aseem Premmay Tumhein were sung.  Now,
after implementing this order, all the madrasas will have to
submit its report to the department.   I
will tell the police to shoot only after asking my caste.
CM's reply to those raising questions on the encounter.
Told the policemen to do their duty.   We are
concerned about the family.  CM Samrat
Choudhary handed over
insurance cheques to the families of policemen killed in road accidents.
During this time, he became emotional after meeting the police families.  The
Chief Minister said that no matter how much
investment is made on Bihar Police,
it is less.  The bigger the police force, the better
governance will be established and Nitish ji has brought
Bihar on the path of good governance.   Good
governance is the only way to prosperity of Bihar.
Some people are worried about themselves.  Some people are
also saying that if the police is doing an encounter then
caste should also be asked in it.
I would tell the policemen to ask the
caste of the person and then fire the bullet.  Don't drive like this.
What common sense do people use?
Elon Musk could become the world's first
trillionaire.  Spcex will
bring the largest IPO in US history.  The valuation was
estimated at ₹1.25 trillion.  Elon Musk may soon
become the world's first trillionaire.
Actually, Elon Musk's rocket and satellite company
is preparing to be listed on the Spcex stock market, which could be the biggest IPO in Wall Street's history.
After its listing, Musk's net worth will cross $1
trillion.
According to the Forbes Billionaires List, Musk is currently the richest person in the world with a
net worth of 807 billion i.e. 77 lakh crore rupees.   On
Wednesday, the company
unveiled plans to list under the SPCX TUCKER symbol.
Due to which other information like the financial leadership of this company has come to
light for the first time.
Hamza Burhan, the terrorist involved in the Pulwama grenade attack, was killed.
Shot by unknown assailants in UK.  Hamza
was a resident of Kashmir and had gone to Pakistan on a visa.
Hamza Burhan, the terrorist involved in the 2020 Pulwama grenade attack, was
shot dead in Pakistan-occupied Kashmir (PoK) and
died on the spot when unidentified assailants opened fire on him outside AIIMS College in Muzaffarabad.  India had
declared Hamza Burhan a terrorist under the UAPA in 2022.  He was considered close to Abu Dujana,
Abu Qasim, Burhanwani and Zakir Musa.
According to the government,
Arjumand Gulzar Dar alias Hamza Burhan
alias Doctor was a resident of Ratnipora area of ​​Pulwama.
23-year-old Hamza
was associated with the terrorist organization Al Badr, which has been
declared a terrorist organization by the government.
Himachal High Court strict on Shimla air connectivity.
Notice issued to the Central Government.
Orders to continue services.  Flight started after 7 months.  The
Himachal High Court has
directed the Central Government regarding the air services of Shimla
that there should be no disruption in the air connectivity of Shimla in future.
Regarding this, the court has told the Central Government that
instructions have been given to file an affidavit till the next hearing.  Chief Justice Gurmeet
Singh Sanghavilia said and the bench of Justice VC
Negi also asked
when the revised flight plan will be implemented and how feasible is the
twin engine helicopter service on the Chandigarh Shimla route
?  The Central Government
told the court that Shimla Airport
is a limited airport as it is located in a hilly area and there is no scope for extending the runway here.
Shankaracharya will buy and
sell cows on Golex, announced a new website on the lines of OX.
He said that he will not let mother cow be slaughtered.
Shankaracharya Swami Abhimukteshwaranand
Saraswati, who is leading a movement against cow slaughter, has now announced online buying and selling of cows.
Shankaracharya has decided
to launch a website named Go Alex Go Alex
through which cows will be
purchased.  Swami Ave Mukteshwarananda
said that we are making a website and
through this website we will buy cows.   Any
cattle breeder or trader who wants to sell his cow can
advertise on the website.
If any Hindu wants to sell his cow,
he should sell it to me.  We
are ready to buy.  We will not allow cows to be slaughtered
and will not allow any cow smuggler to buy cows.
MP, UP, Haryana have temperatures as high as Egypt and Saudi
Arabia.  The temperature reached 48 degrees Celsius just four days before the nine-day mark.
Eight school girls fainted due to heat in UP.
Nine times starting from 25th May.
But even before that the temperature has reached 48° Celsius.
This figure has been
recorded in Banda, Uttar Pradesh and in
terms of temperature, Banda was the third hottest city in the world on May 20.
Only Aswan in Egypt, at 49.4°
C, and Arafat in Saudi Arabia, at 48.4°
C, recorded temperatures higher than Banda.
Khajuraho ranked fourth among the top five cities with the highest temperature in the world
with 47.4° Celsius.
Here in Balrampur, due to extreme heat,
eight girl students fainted while studying in Kasturba Gandhi School and all of them
complained of vomiting, headache and fainting.
He is undergoing treatment.  Meanwhile, 16 cities in Uttar
Pradesh, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Haryana,
Delhi, Punjab, Odisha and Maharashtra
also recorded temperatures above 46°C.  As the
temperature rises, anger
and irritability increase.  There may be problem of less sleep
and sometimes focus on work
decreases.  In fact, when the temperature is high,
more energy is spent to keep the body cool
and the
balance of feel-good hormones in the brain gets disturbed.
Doctor from Latur arrested in NEET paper leak case.
Bought guess paper for my son.   The
main accused M Sir was going to open a school and college.
CBI has arrested
a doctor from Latur, Maharashtra in the NEET paper leak case.  It
is alleged that Dr. Manoj
Sirure had purchased case papers for his son from RCC Coaching
director and accused Shivraj Motegaonkar alias
M Sir.  CBI has
arrested him after interrogation in Pune
and the information has come to light now and
this is the first arrest of any parent in this case.
This is the 11th arrest in the NEET paper leak case,
and before this, six people were arrested from Maharashtra,
three from Rajasthan and one from Haryana,
including two women.  On the other hand,
new revelations are continuously being made in this case and the
CBI investigation has now revealed that Shivraj was
preparing to open a school and college on 8 acres of land in Latur.
Cockroach Janata Party's ex-account
blocked.  13.4 million followers on Instagram in 6 days.
This is one and a half times the number of BJP followers
and more than that of Congress.
Cockroach Janata Party (CJP), formed six days ago, had more than
1.34 crore followers on Instagram by 2:00 pm on Thursday.
This is
more than any other political party in the country.
Congress has 1.33 crore and
BJP has 87 lakh on Instagram.  Aam Aadmi Party has more than 87
lakh followers and CPI(M) has more than 2.35 lakh followers.  Let us
tell you that this party, formed in
protest against the cockroach statement of CJI Suryakant,
also had more than 1.93 lakh
followers on its account.  However, the
X account was blocked around 12:00 pm on Thursday.
CJP founder Abhijeet Deepak said
that what was feared happened.  CJP's
ex-account was banned in India.
According to X, it has taken action in India on the basis of standing
rules, court orders or legal complaints.
Congress MLA in Tamil Nadu
said Rahul Zindabad during oath taking.  The Governor
interrupted him.  He said this is not part of the oath.
23 ministers joined the Vijay cabinet.   There was
again controversy in the cabinet expansion of Vijay government in Tamil Nadu.  Actually,
Congress MLA Rajesh Kumar said
Kamaraj Amar Rahe during the oath taking ceremony.  Long live Rajiv Gandhi.
Said long live people's leader Rahul Gandhi.
Governor Rajendra Vishwanath Arlekar
interrupted this.  The Governor said that this is
not part of your oath.  Another controversy
also arose regarding playing Tamil songs.
Tamil's state Tamil Thai Vaithu was
played last in the ceremony.  In previous governments, this used to be the first to be
played.  CM Vijay's cabinet has been expanded in Tamil Nadu
and 23
MLAs have taken oath as ministers.
Two Congress MLAs are also included in this.
Air India Delhi Bengaluru flight
hits runway.  Accident during landing.
Scratched on the back side.  Passengers and
crew members are safe.  It is reported that Air
India
flight AI 2651 from Delhi to Bengaluru hit the runway
while landing at Kempegowda International Airport on Thursday.  The
rear part of the flight
touched the ground.  The phenomenon is
called tail strike in aviation language.  The flight was
landed safely and
pictures of the incident have also surfaced on social media.
In which a scratch is visible on the rear part of the flight.  There were
passengers on board the flight and no crew member
or crew member was reported injured in the incident.
Dress code will be applicable in universities and colleges of UP.  The
Governor said that
discrimination among students will reduce.  An environment of equality will be created.
Dress code will be implemented in all universities and colleges of UP.
Governor Anandiben Patel has
taken this decision during a review meeting at Raj Bhavan.
He said that implementation of dress code will
reduce the feeling of rich-poor or social discrimination among the students.  When all the students are
seen in similar dress, an atmosphere of equality will
also be created.  The Governor has
pledged to make girls and women self-reliant.
He has given instructions to start employment related courses in colleges from the new session.
He said that the
girl students should do skill
development along with studies.  For this, courses like beautician
training, mehndi, GST, accounting,
bindi making and food product preparation will be
started.
This time there are chances of drought,
rainfall will be reduced by 20%.  Heat wave will last for 30 days in Bihar this season.  The
mercury will cross 45° Celsius.   There is
severe heat in Bihar and the mercury has
crossed 40° Celsius.  There is little hope of
relief from the scorching heat for the next 8 days
and this season the heat
wave will continue for 30 days.  The worrying thing is that there is a
possibility of drought in Bihar this year.  Along with this, one may
also have to endure severe heat.
Water temperatures are rising here around the equator in the Pacific Ocean.
Due to this, Super El Nino conditions are likely to persist from mid-May to July till winter.   When
this happens, the
warm winds coming from the Pacific Ocean block the
moist and cold winds flowing towards India from the Indian Ocean and the Arabian Sea
and due to this cold wind,
rain occurs during the monsoon.  Stopping the wind
means there will be less rain.
According to meteorologists, monsoon is
likely to arrive in Bihar on June 8-10.  Usually
it comes around 15th June.  The
southwest monsoon is
likely to hit Kerala on May 26 and according to meteorologist Ashish Kumar,
Bihar is
likely to receive less than normal rainfall during the monsoon this year too.   The
normal monsoon rainfall in Bihar
is 992.2 mm.  According to meteorologists, this
year there is a possibility of about 20% less rainfall than normal in Bihar.  The
situation may become even more serious if El Nino and Super El Nino affect the monsoon.
Today's thought:
Not having a degree is also beneficial
because those with degrees do the same work.
But those who do not have a degree can do anything.  Do let
us know how you liked this video
in the comment section.  If you like the video then please
like and share the video and to
watch such interesting videos
subscribe to our channel Jio News
[Music] and press the bell icon and do
check our [Music] playlist and community tab to watch our old and latest videos.  So see you
in the next video.  Thank you for now.
[music]